{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "This actor played a Mexican revolutionary in Viva Zapata! and Mark Antony in the 1953\nJulius Caesar. He utters the last words \"the horror…the horror\" in his role as Kurtz in\nApocalypse Now. This star of The Wild One sent American Indian activist Sacheen Littlefeather\nto accept his Oscar for another role. For 10 points, name this portrayer of Vito Corleone in The\nGodfather.",
      "answer": [
        "Marlon Brando",
        "Brando"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "(TIEBREAKER EXAMPLE QUESTION) The Qing Dynasty was founded by what ethnic group from the north of China, which\nmandated that all Han Chinese wear their hair in queues?",
      "answer": [
        "Manchus",
        "Manchurians"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "(EXAMPLE BONUS QUESTION) Japan underwent an internal political crisis over invading Korea in the Seikanron, a\ncomponent of what larger movement to modernize Japan and replace the Tokugawa shogunate\nwith a constitutional monarchy?",
      "answer": "the Meiji Restoration"
    },
    {
      "question": "This nation was invaded by Huang Taiji in 1636 as the Qing [CHING] dynasty sought to solidify its\nwar against the Ming. In 1592, Toyotomi Hideyoshi’s invasion of this nation was disrupted by enemy turtle\nships. The Joseon dynasty ruled it until 1897, and it was annexed by Japan in 1910. For ten points, name\nthis East Asian peninsula split after World War II by Soviet and American agreement into two countries\nwith capitals Pyongyang and Seoul.",
      "answer": [
        "Korean Peninsula",
        "Korea"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Supporters of this party were victims of the White Terror Massacre. The Xian [SHEE-ahn] incident\nwas perpetrated by members of this party. The Gang of Four consisted of members of this party and were\nlater found guilty of treason near the end of one of this party’s efforts, the Cultural Revolution. For ten\npoints, name this ruling party of an Asian nation once led by Mao Zedong.",
      "answer": [
        "Communist Party of China",
        "Chinese Communist Party",
        "China Communist",
        "Chinese Communist",
        "CCP"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "(TIEBREAKER BONUS QUESTION) What final Japanese shogunate which was overthrown in the Meiji Restoration?",
      "answer": [
        "Tokugawa Shogunate",
        "Tokugawa"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This rebellion was inspired by the pamphlet “Good Words for Exhorting the Age” and originated\namong the Hakka people. The Ever Victorious Army was essential in putting down this rebellion under\nthe leadership of General Gordon, who gained a nickname from that campaign. This rebellion’s leader,\na man who claimed to be the younger brother of Jesus, was found dead in his palace in Nanjing. For\nten points, name this 19th century rebellion, led by Hong Xiuquan, that tried to establish a Heavenly\nKingdom in China.",
      "answer": [
        "Taiping Rebellion",
        "Taiping",
        "Taiping Uprising",
        "Taiping Civil War"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This man gathered a small handful of early followers at a deer park near Sarnath. During one sermon, this man was not understood by anyone except Mahakashyapa, who smiled when this man held up a white lotus. After this figure’s enlightenment, he described the Eightfold Path as a method of escaping samsara and attaining nirvana. For ten points, name this religious figure whose teachings form the basis for an Asian religion.",
      "answer": [
        "Siddhartha Gautama",
        "Gautama",
        "the Buddha"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Japan’s capture of this location led to the largest surrender of British forces in history. The British East India Company annexed this island from the Sultanate of Johor, allowing Stamford Raffles to found a trading post that has developed into the southernmost of the four “Asian Tiger” economies. For ten points, name this island city-state that was expelled from Malaysia in 1965.",
      "answer": "Singapore"
    },
    {
      "question": "During this war, Operations Killer and Ripper were ordered by Matthew Ridgway. Fighting over the Iron Triangle in this war took place in the Battles of Triangle Hill and Pork Chop Hill. In this war, US F-86 Sabres fought over MiG Alley and an intervention by Chinese forces over the Yalu River led to the dismissal of Douglas MacArthur. The United States led UN forces to the 38th parallel in, for ten points, what war fought over an East Asian peninsula that is now divided into North and South countries?",
      "answer": [
        "Korean War",
        "Korean"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "One of these policies named for Walker improved relations with Great Britain after the repeal of the\nCorn Laws. One of these policies was described as an abomination and led to the Nullification Crisis, while\nthe Smoot-Hawley example made the Great Depression worse by slowing global trade. NAFTA restricts\nCanada, Mexico, and the United States from using, for ten points, what type of tax on imported goods?",
      "answer": [
        "tariff",
        "Walker Tariff",
        "Tariff of Abominations",
        "Smoot-Hawley Tariff"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Rather than initially perform this action, Kantaro Suzuki decided to respond to an ultimatum by\n“killing it with silence,” or mokusatsu. Commemorations of this action are held on August 15th and\nSeptember 2nd, recognizing either the Jewel Voice Broadcast or the official signing of documents on board\nthe USS Missouri. For ten points, name this event that ended fighting in World War II, four months after\na similar event in Germany.",
      "answer": [
        "the surrender of Japan in World War II",
        "surrender of Japan",
        "V-J Day",
        "V-J",
        "Victory in Japan Day"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This government adopted a motto from the Warring States period, “enrich the state, strengthen\nthe military.” This government abolished the han system, returning land to the central government, and\nabolished the existing class structure in the Charter Oath. This government’s power was solidified after\nthe Boshin War, in which samurai loyal to the Tokugawa Shogunate were defeated. For ten points, name\nthis modernizing government that ruled Japan after the 1868 restoration of the emperor.",
      "answer": [
        "Meiji",
        "Meiji government",
        "Meiji Restoration",
        "the government of Emperor Meiji"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "(TIEBREAKER BONUS QUESTION) What southernmost Japanese prefecture with capital at Naha was occupied by the United\nStates until 1972 and still retains over 50,000 US soldiers?",
      "answer": [
        "Okinawa Prefecture",
        "Okinawa"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "(TIEBREAKER BONUS QUESTION) What Chinese revolutionary founded the Republic of China and outlined his Three\nPrinciples of the People in a 1905 speech?",
      "answer": [
        "Sun Yat-sen",
        "Sun"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "During this event, John Indian was ordered to prepare a cake made of urine to feed to a dog. Cotton\nMather addressed a letter to the instigators of this event warning them against using “spectral evidence.”\nOne part of this event focused on the slave Tituba’s alleged spiritual influence over young children. Twenty\npeople died during the hysteria of, for ten points, what late 17th century tragedy in Massachusetts over\nsupposed evil magic?",
      "answer": "Salem witch trials"
    },
    {
      "question": "One of this man’s works was compiled by Tribonian, John the Cappadocian, and others. A\ndisagreement at chariot races during his reign grew into the Nika Riots, which he put down at the\nencouragement of his wife Theodora. This ruler’s general Belisarius recaptured Northern Africa and\nmuch of Italy, and this man codified Roman law into the Corpus Juris Civilis. For ten points, name this\nByzantine emperor who built the Hagia Sophia.",
      "answer": [
        "Justinian the Great",
        "Justinian",
        "Justinian I"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Foreign intervention in this conflict prompted the battles of Outpost Harry and Pork Chop Hill.\nDuring this war, Matthew Ridgeway replaced a general who masterminded a decisive landing at Inchon,\nDouglas MacArthur. A demilitarized zone was created after an armistice was signed, though there has\nstill been no peace treaty to end this war. For ten points, name this 1950s conflict on an Asian peninsula.",
      "answer": [
        "Korean War",
        "Korean"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Members of this class began the Rokugo rebellion after the defeat of their lord. These people, who\nreceived stipends in units of rice called koku, first rose to prominence during the Kamakura shogunate.\nMembers of this class who were no longer employed were known as ronin. These warriors had the right\nto bear katanas and followed the bushido code of honor. For ten points, name this noble military class in\nmedieval Japan.",
      "answer": "samurai"
    },
    {
      "question": "A precursor to this law known as the 15 Passenger Bill was resolved by Richard Angell after it was struck down by Rutherford Hayes. The Magnuson Act repealed this law, which negated immigration provisions in the Burlingame Treaty. “Yellow Peril” motivated this legislation, which was passed after increasing immigration of an ethnic group following the 1849 California Gold Rush. For ten points, name this 1882 law that banned citizens from an Asian country from entering the US.",
      "answer": "Chinese Exclusion Act of 1882"
    },
    {
      "question": "Trade in this desert declined after the Battle of Tondibi, relegating merchants to routes such as Azalai and Taoudenni. While traveling from Sijilmasa to the Oualata Oasis, Ibn Battuta wrote of how Berber guides were influential in the trade of this desert. The vital Taghaza salt mines were located in this desert, where dromedaries were domesticated for travel. For ten points, name this large desert that Arab traders crossed to reach West Africa.",
      "answer": "Sahara Desert"
    },
    {
      "question": "Azizul Haque and Hem Chandra Bose subdivided these objects into 1024 types to develop the Henry Classification System of sorting them. Excavating pottery in Japan piqued Henry Fauld’s interest in these objects. Marcello Malpighi documented friction ridges in these structures, which Francis Galton divided into loops, arches, and whorls. For ten points, forensic science studies the identification of what patterns that are unique to every human and often left at crime scenes?",
      "answer": "fingerprints"
    },
    {
      "question": "Thispositionwastoberevered,andthebarbariansweretobeexpelled,accordingtotheslogan“Sonno Joi.” Scholars and politicians have debated whether the song “Kimigayo” celebrates this figure. Under the Insei, the holder of this position retired to become a Buddhist monk but still held power as a Joko. According to legend, Jimmu was the first holder of this position, whose holders are given a posthumous name reflecting the era in which they ruled. For ten points, what ruler sits on the Chrysanthemum Throne as the leader of an East Asian country?",
      "answer": [
        "Emperor of Japan",
        "Tenno",
        "Mikado"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Fear of rebellion motivated this colony’s elite to establish a Slave Code in 1705 that hardened the race line in this colony. John Punch was enslaved in this colony and was the first documented African slave in the English colonies. A rebellion in this colony against William Berkeley united African slaves and English servants under Nathaniel Bacon. For ten points, name this plantation-based colony where, in 1676, Jamestown was burned to the ground.",
      "answer": "Virginia"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man ordered that the coastal village of Tercanabal on the Sangres Peninsula be repopulated so that he could build a villa there. In order to search Africa for Prester John, this man convinced his father to conquer Ceuta in 1415. An expedition led by Gil Eannes, supported by this man, crossed Cape Bojador. For ten points, name this 15th century Portuguese prince whose funding helped start the Age of Discovery.",
      "answer": "Prince Henry the Navigator"
    },
    {
      "question": "The South African Police Service murdered 17 strikers who extracted this commodity in the Marikana Massacre. Great Zimbabwe merchants often traded this commodity for porcelain and silk with the Sultanate of Kilwa. A colony named for this commodity first fell to a European power after multiple Anglo-Ashanti Wars. For ten points, name this commodity that, along with salt, was the primary trade good of medieval and early modern West Africa.",
      "answer": "gold"
    },
    {
      "question": "This policy was enacted under the leadership of D.F. Mala and his National Party. In accordance with this policy, the movement of citizens were restricted by the Pass Laws. People protesting this policy were massacred at Sharpeville and Soweto. In 1993, F.W. de Klerk shared a Nobel Peace Prize for helping to end this policy. Nelson Mandela opposed, for ten points, what South African system of racial segregation?",
      "answer": "apartheid"
    },
    {
      "question": "This dynasty was founded by an emperor who established a secret police force known as the Embroidered Uniform Guard. That emperor’s grandson died at the hands of his uncle, Zhu Di, who became the Yongle [yong-luh] Emperor. The Yongle Emperor employed the eunuch Zheng He [zhung-huh] to command his treasure fleet and successfully spread Chinese influence as far as the Persian Gulf. For ten points, name this Chinese dynasty that ruled from 1368 to 1644, perhaps best known today for its fine ceramics.",
      "answer": "Ming Dynasty T"
    },
    {
      "question": "This ethnic group's Borjigin clan employed Al-aud-Din to construct counterweighted trebuchets during a conquest that unseated the child-emperor Zhao Bing. This group destroyed the Jin under the leadership of Ogedei, and established their own dynasty after defeating the Song. For ten points, name this Asian civilization that established China's Yuan dynasty under the leadership of Kublai, the grandson of Genghis Khan.",
      "answer": "Mongols Page 1 of 10"
    },
    {
      "question": "In 1982, two laid-off Chrysler workers killed a man of this ethnic group in Highland Park, Michigan due to their anger at their company being outcompeted by the Japanese auto industry. This people group, who were killed en masse in the Rock Springs Massacre, experienced California's discriminatory Anti-Coolie Act. An 1882 \"Exclusion Act\" was passed to limit immigration by, for ten points, what Asian ethnic group, many of whom immigrated during the late Qing [[CHING]] Dynasty?",
      "answer": "Chinese-Americans"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During this century, the Ottoman Empire's Tulip Period began with the Treaty of Passarowitz\n(pr. puh-SAH-roe-vits). At the end of this century, the White Lotus Rebellion broke out in\nChina. The Battle of Plassey and the Black Hole of Calcutta took place in this century. For 10\npoints, identify this century in which Britain took control of Canada after the French and Indian\nWar.",
        "answer": "18th, 18th century AD, 1700s"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Battle of Plassey weakened what Islamic dynasty that had ruled in India since\n1526, transferring effective control of most of India to the British East India Company?",
        "answer": "Mughal, Mughal Dynasty"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This city’s former troops revolted against it in the Mercenary War. As a result, this city's\nleader Hanno the Great was displaced by the rising Barcid dynasty, whose members included\nHamilcar and Hasdrubal. This city lost the Battle of Zama to Scipio Africanus. For 10 points\nname this ancient North African city which was defeated by Rome in three Punic Wars.",
        "answer": "Carthage"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The site of Carthage is in which present day African country, whose soccer team is\nthus known as the Carthage Eagles?",
        "answer": "Tunisia"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man hid out at Liliesleaf Farm after the Treason Trial, where he organized the militant\ngroup Spear of the Nation. He gave the \"I Am Prepared to Die\" speech at the Rivonia Trial,\nwhich led to his lengthy imprisonment on Robben Island. For 10 points, name this man who\nultimately worked with F.W. de Klerk to end the apartheid system in South Africa.",
        "answer": [
          "Nelson Rolihlahla Mandela",
          "Mandela",
          "Nelson Mandela"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Mandela's Spear of the Nation was the paramilitary wing of what anti-apartheid group,\nwhich has been the governing political party of South Africa since 1994?",
        "answer": [
          "ANC",
          "African National Congress"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A portion of this structure was built in the contested Ordos region. The early heqin [huh-CHEEN]\nsystem allowed the Xiongnu [tchee-ONG-noo] to rule the area north of this structure. The Jiayu Pass\nserves as the end of one section of this structure built by the Ming dynasty to defend against Mongol\nattacks. For ten points, name this massive series of Chinese defensive fortifications.",
        "answer": [
          "Great Wall of China",
          "Great Wall"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The deal with the Xiongnu occurred under the ruler of this dynasty. The history of this dynasty,\nwhich also names China’s largest ethnic group, was chronicled by Sima Qian [su-mah chee-en].",
        "answer": [
          "Han Dynasty",
          "Han"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The patronage of Gushi Khan increased the power of the holders of this position. A delegate of one\nholder of this position was forced at gunpoint to ratify the Seventeen Point Agreement. Men who hold this\nposition are thought to be incarnations of Avalokiteshvara. The current holder of this position, Tenzin\nGyatso, currently lives in exile in India. For ten points, name this position, the spiritual leader of Tibetan\nBuddhism.",
        "answer": "Dalai Lama"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This other form of Buddhism, which uses koans to teach Buddhist principles, is commonly\npracticed in Japan.",
        "answer": [
          "Zen Buddhism",
          "Zen"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This government was advised by the Roju and used red seal ships for trade. Only the nanban were\nallowed by this government to enter its country, as per Sakoku law, which banned foreign influence. This\nperiod began when a leader defeated forces loyal to Toyotomi Hideyoshi at the Battle of Sekigahara,\nand ended when Matthew Perry’s black ships arrived. Ieyasu founded, for ten points, which Japanese\nshogunate that was ended by the 1868 Meiji restoration?",
        "answer": [
          "Tokugawa shogunate",
          "Tokugawa",
          "Edo period",
          "Edo"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Tokugawa put an end to the period of sengoku jidai, a period of warring states in Japan. The\nprocess of unification began with this leader, who overthrew the Ashikaga before dying at Honnoji.",
        "answer": [
          "Oda Nobunaga",
          "Oda"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "These devices were used in “596,” an event at Lop Nur. The Dimona Institute in the Negev is widely\nsuspected to be used for manufacturing these devices, which South Africa no longer possesses. “Smiling\nBuddha” was the codename for India’s proof of possession of these devices. A “triad” of submarines,\naircraft, and ballistic missiles are used to deploy, for ten points, what weapons that have not been used in\nwar since 1945, when Harry Truman ordered their use against Japan?",
        "answer": [
          "nuclear weapons",
          "nuclear",
          "atom bombs",
          "hydrogen bombs",
          "atomic bombs"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This treaty, signed in 1968, attempts to prevent the spread of nuclear weapons. It recognizes five\nnations that can have nuclear weapons, but has not been signed by India, Pakistan, or Israel.",
        "answer": [
          "Treaty on the Non-Proliferation of Nuclear Weapons",
          "Non-Proliferation",
          "Non-Proliferation Treaty",
          "NPT"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Dorgon oversaw the ascension of this dynasty. The Hundred Days’ Reforms and the Self-Strengthening\nMovement were attempts to modernize under this dynasty. It required its subjects to wear their hair in\na queue and divided its military into the Eight Banners. An empress of this dynasty, Cixi [tsee-chee],\nsupported the anti-western Boxer Rebellion. For ten points, name this dynasty that ruled China from\n1648 to 1911, the last imperial dynasty.",
        "answer": [
          "Qing Dynasty",
          "Qing",
          "Manchu Dynasty",
          "Manchu"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Qing Dynasty, like all Chinese dynasties, required those approaching the emperor to perform\nthis submissive action as a gesture of respect. Lord Macartney supposedly refused to perform this action,\ncreating tension between Britain and China.",
        "answer": [
          "kowtow",
          "kneeling with one’s forehead touching the ground",
          "bowing with one’s forehead touching the ground"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The Ringle Report opposed this policy, which was implemented under John DeWitt at facilities like\nTule Lake and Manzanar. 1942’s Executive Order 9066 instituted this policy, whose constitutionality was\nupheld in the Supreme Court decision Korematsu v. United States. John DeWitt testified that “American\ncitizenship does not necessarily determine loyalty” in support of, for ten points, what policy in which over\n100,000 Asian-Americans were forcibly detained in camps during World War II?",
        "answer": [
          "internment of Japanese-Americans",
          "internment of Japanese"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Japanese immigration to the United States took off after the passage of this 1882 act, which\nsuspended immigration from another Asian nation and stranded immigrants on Angel Island.",
        "answer": [
          "Chinese Exclusion Act",
          "Chinese Exclusion"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This organization ran the Addiscombe College for prospective officers in the Presidency armies. This\norganization was opposed by governors called Polygars. This organization was opposed by Tipu Sultan,\nwho fought four Mysore Wars against it. Its ascent to power began after Robert Clive won the Battle of\nPlassey against the Nawab of Bengal, who had orchestrated the Black Hole of Calcutta. For ten points,\nname this joint stock company that conquered most of the Indian subcontinent for England.",
        "answer": [
          "British East India Company",
          "British East India"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The British East India Company lost control of India after this event, in which Indian soldiers\nrevolted after being given rifle cartridges greased with animal fats.",
        "answer": [
          "Sepoy Mutiny",
          "Sepoy",
          "Indian Rebellion of 1857"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During this dynasty, the heqin [huh-CHEEN] system of using marriages for peace was used to repel an attack by Xiongnu [shong-nu] Emperor Modu Chanyu. Sima Qian [see-ma chee-ahn] wrote the Records of the Grand Historian during the reign of this dynasty’s Emperor Wu. The Trung Sisters attempted to liberate Vietnam from this dynasty, which was founded by Liu Bang. For ten points, name this dynasty that shares its name with China’s largest ethnic group.",
        "answer": "Han Dynasty"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Han Dynasty was followed by this tumultuous period, during which the warrior Cao Cao [tsow-tsow] was active. The Jin Dynasty’s conquest of Eastern Wu ended this period.",
        "answer": "Three Kingdoms period"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "According to myth, this nation was created by two gods named “He-who-invites” and “She-who-is- invited” and the help of a giant spear. This country is the birthplace of a religion that uses purification rituals called harae [ha-rah-ay] and whose holiest shrine is rebuilt every 20 years. In 1995, a doomsday cult carried out a sarin attack in this nation’s largest city. The Ise [ee-say] and Yasukuni shrines can be found in, for ten points, what Asian country where Shinto developed in the 8th century and is practiced in Tokyo?",
        "answer": "Japan"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In Japan, Shinbutsu-shugo is a syncretism, or mixed religion, of aspects of Shinto with this other world religion. The Zen school of this religion is also widely practiced in Japan.",
        "answer": [
          "Buddhism",
          "Zen Buddhism"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One of these systems was invented in the 15th century by Sejong the Great of the Joseon Dynasty; its\n40 elements can be combined into over 11 thousand blocks. The oldest of these systems is an abjad with\n22 entries; that Phoenician system inspired modern examples such as Greek, Cyrillic, and Latin. The first\ntwo entries in the Hebrew system inspires the name of, for ten points, what term for a set of letters used\nto write a language?",
        "answer": "alphabet"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Sejong the Great invented hangul, the alphabet for this Asian language. It was spoken in the\nJoseon dynasty, and it has undergone significant changes over the last 70 years after the splitting of the\ntwo countries in which it is primarily spoken.",
        "answer": [
          "Korean language",
          "Korean",
          "Korea",
          "South Korea",
          "North Korea",
          "South and North Korea"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During this century, the political slogan “sonno joi” responded to the arrival of the “black ships.” The Convention of Kanagawa was signed during this century, ending a longstanding policy of isolation. The Tokugawa Shogunate was overthrown in this century as part of a restoration of imperial power in Japan. For ten points, name this century in which the Japanese navy purchased the CSS Stonewall four years after the end of the American Civil War.",
        "answer": [
          "19th century",
          "1800s"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The aforementioned 1868 restoration of imperial power was led by, and named for, this Japanese emperor.",
        "answer": [
          "Emperor Meiji",
          "Mutsuhito",
          "Meiji Restoration",
          "similar terms"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Masahiko Nomi linked these things to personality, influenced by imperialist Japan’s use of these things to promote racial superiority. Karl Landsteiner developed a system for classifying these things, which can be “universal donors” or “universal recipients.” The absence or presence of the Rhesus factor’s “little d antigen” on these things denotes whether they are positive or negative. The compatibility of a transfusion is determined by, for ten points, what medical quality that comes in, A, B, AB, and O classifications?",
        "answer": [
          "blood types",
          "blood groups"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The ABO blood type system is based on the presence of antigens on the surfaces of these cells within the blood. Anton van Leeuwenhoek described seeing these cells under a microscope in 1674.",
        "answer": "red blood cells or erythrocytes"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This type of military maneuver was introduced to Japan by Takeda Shinjin and was defeated by Oda Nobunaga with the use of firearms at the first “modern” Japanese battle, the Battle of Nagashino. Gustavus Adolphus was killed at Lubeck while leading one of these maneuvers. These maneuvers were the hammer in the Macedonian “hammer and anvil” strategy, and they were used as opening maneuvers in battles for centuries until infantry squares rendered them obsolete. For ten points, name this military maneuver that involves a full speed ride at an enemy force.",
        "answer": [
          "cavalry charge",
          "clear knowledge equivalents"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This battle in Flanders was named after the objects that littered the battlefield after a failed French cavalry charge led by Robert II of Artois [ar-twah].",
        "answer": [
          "Battle of the Golden Spurs",
          "the Battle of Courtrai"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The Sakai Incident marked the first time a European observed this practice. To preserve dignity, a version of this practice for women involved knee-binding. In this practice, a fan would sometimes be replaced for a tanto, and a second would decapitate the victim of this practice. For ten points, name this form of suicide employed by disgraced Japanese samurai.",
        "answer": "seppuku or harakiri"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This Japanese author of The Temple of the Golden Pavilion committed seppuku after a failed 1970 coup d’etat.",
        "answer": [
          "Yukio Mishima or Kimitake Hiraoka",
          "either name in either order"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During this war, one side captured Water Works Redoubt and 203 Meter Hill while closing in on an important harbor. British trawlers were mistaken for torpedo boats and fired on in this war’s Dogger Bank Incident, and 600,000 soldiers fought in Manchuria in this war’s Battle of Mukden. After an invading fleet was decimated at Tsushima Strait, Teddy Roosevelt brokered the Treaty of Portsmouth to end, for ten points, what 1904-1905 war between two Asian empires?",
        "answer": "Russo-Japanese War"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Russo-Japanese War opened with a surprise night attack on the Russian fleet as it was anchored at what Manchurian port?",
        "answer": [
          "Port Arthur",
          "Lushun City",
          "Ryojun"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This colony developed after civilians rejected a 1923 referendum to become the fifth province of South Africa. Leaders of this colony decided to ally with Antonio Salazar to resist the policy of “no independence before majority rule.” This colony issued the Unilateral Declaration of Independence under Ian Smith, sparking a civil war. The Lancaster House Agreement ended the Bush War in, for ten points, what British colony that became Zimbabwe?",
        "answer": "Rhodesia"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The namesake of Rhodesia, Cecil Rhodes, planned an epic railway to connect these two African cities.",
        "answer": "Cape Town, South Africa and Cairo, Egypt"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During this event, a bannerman under En Hai assassinated German diplomat Clemens von Ketteler. In this conflict, foreign citizens were besieged for 55-days while taking refuge in the Legation Quarter. Sir Claude MacDonald commanded the Eight-Nation Alliance in response to this rebellion. During this rebellion, a provisional government was set-up in Tianjin to combat the Qing dynasty. The Righteous and Harmonious Fists launched, for ten points, what 1898 uprising against Western colonialism in China?",
        "answer": "Boxer Rebellion"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Boxer Rebellion was praised by this man, the founding father of the Republic of China.",
        "answer": "Sun Yat-Sen"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Claudius Gothicus died during one of these events named for Cyprian. A diplomatic mission to China may have caused one of these events that likely claimed the life of Lucius Verus. Over 5 million people may have died in an event of this type that began under, and is named for, Antoninus Pius. Galen observed that fevers and boils were common symptoms of one of these events. For ten points, name these events, massive outbreaks of disease.",
        "answer": "plagues"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "A 541 AD plague occurred during the reign of this Byzantine Emperor, causing the reversal of Belisarius” conquests.",
        "answer": [
          "Justinian I",
          "Justinian the Great"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The first person to hold this position once vomited on stage during an election debate. John MacDonald was the second-longest holder of this position, after only William Lyon Mackenzie King. Another holder of this position enforced the only peacetime usage of the War Measures Act in response D to the October Crisis and was the father of the current holder of this position, who succeeded Stephen Harper. For ten points, name this position currently held by Justin Trudeau.",
        "answer": "Prime Minister of Canada"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Canadian Prime Minister Lester B. Pearson won the 1957 Nobel Peace Prize for his role in resolving the conflict over what strategic waterway?",
        "answer": "Suez Canal T"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Individuals who manufactured these objects went on strike in London in the 1880s due to increasing cases of “phossy jaw” caused by the white phosphorus used on these objects. Samuel Jones popularized Lucifers, a type of these objects that relies on friction, and Gustaf Pasch developed the “safety” version of these objects to prevent unintentional combustion. Hans Christian Andersen wrote a fairy tale about F a young girl selling, for ten points, these objects that produce a flame when a piece of wood or paper including a flammable substance is struck against a rough surface.",
        "answer": "Matchsticks"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The earliest references to matches from 14th century China describe pinewood sticks coated with this odiferous element, atomic number 16, referred to in the Bible as “brimstone.”",
        "answer": "Sulfur A"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The Crippsmissionwasafailedattempttosecurethiscolony'sfullcooperationinits colonizer's World War Two efforts. This colony's Lucknow Pact united its rival Muslim League and a namesake National Congress. The last viceroy of this colony was Lord Mountbatten, who withheld support forthecreationofanindependentPakistan.Gainingits independence as the culmination ofthe3JunePlanwas,fortenpoints,whatsubcontinental British colony? ANSWER:India(accept the BritishRaj; accept DirectRule inIndia; accept Crown Rule in India; acceptIndian Empire; prompt on \"Bharata\") BONUS: This ally of Mahatma Gandhi and opponent of Muhammad Ali Jinnah was the first and longest-serving prime minister of independent India.",
        "answer": "JawaharlalNehru] 5 This mansupposedlycrossedachannelwhilewearingchainmailinataletoldbyhis rival, Unferth. A band of thanes who abandoned this king after encountering a dragon are later exiled by his successor, Wiglaf ]. This man tearsthearmsoffadescendant of Cain who terrorizes theHallofHeorot]ofKingHrothgar]. For ten points, name this hero of the Geats ] whodefeatsthemonsterGrendelina namesake epic poem. ANSWER:Beowulf"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Beowulf is written in what Middle Age language, virtually unreadable to contemporary speakers without study? ANSWER:Old English(acceptAnglo-Saxon; acceptEnglisc;prompt on \"English\") 2021-22 C Set History (6) In this state, former U.S. Army soldier Kevin Baugh [[BAW]] founded a 1.28 acre micronation knownastheRepublicofMolossia.ThediscoveryoftheComstockLodeledtoa mining boom around this state's Virginia City. As a response to the Great Depression, this statelegalized\"gaming\"inthe1930s.TheCarsonCityconventionledtothestatehoodof,for ten points, what western U.S. state? ANSWER:Nevada BONUS: The statehood of Nevada was rushedinanattempttoguaranteeAbrahamLincoln's victory over this Copperhead DemocratandformercommandinggeneraloftheU.S.Armyin the presidential election of 1864.",
        "answer": "George BrintonMcClellan"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This dynasty established hegemony after Emperor Tang won the Battle of Mingtiao [[MING-TYAO]] during the first \"Noble Revolution\" in East Asian history. This dynasty made its capital the city of Yin, near modern Anyang. During this dynasty, mystics began using turtle shells, or \"oracle bones,\" for divination. Following the Battle of Muye [[MOO-YUH]], the Zhou [[ZHOH]] overthrew, for ten points, what Chinese dynasty, the first with extensive archaeological records?",
        "answer": [
          "Shang Dynasty or Shāngcháo",
          "Yin Dynasty",
          "Yīndài before mentioned"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Shang succeeded what semi-legendary dynasty founded by Yu the Great, the first traditional dynasty in Chinese historiography?",
        "answer": "Xia ] Dynasty or Xiàcháo"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "HERBERT HOOVER",
      "prompt": "Name the person or event from the life or presidency of Hoover that was...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "The four-term New Deal architect who succeeded him",
          "answer": "Franklin Delano Roosevelt, F Roosevelt, FDR"
        },
        {
          "question": "The Chicago mob kingpin convicted of tax evasion",
          "answer": "Al Capone, Capone, Alphonse Gabriel Capone"
        },
        {
          "question": "His \"Silent\" predecessor in the White House",
          "answer": "Calvin Coolidge, Coolidge, John Calvin Coolidge"
        },
        {
          "question": "The East Asian language he spoke, along with more native speakers than any other language",
          "answer": "Chinese, Mandarin"
        },
        {
          "question": "The prestigious California university which he attended in its first year",
          "answer": "Stanford, Stanford University"
        },
        {
          "question": "The popular nickname for the stock market crash of October 29, 1929",
          "answer": "Black Tuesday"
        },
        {
          "question": "The disastrous 1930 tariff bill which worsened the Depression",
          "answer": "Smoot-Hawley Tariff, Smoot-Hawley, Hawley-Smoot, Hawley-Smoot Tariff"
        },
        {
          "question": "A group of World War I veterans who marched on Washington",
          "answer": "Bonus Army"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "THE MONGOLS",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Conquered a large empire primarily on which continent, including China and Persia?",
          "answer": "Asia"
        },
        {
          "question": "Mastered the art of combat atop what riding animals?",
          "answer": "horses"
        },
        {
          "question": "Were united into an empire by what man, born Temujin?",
          "answer": [
            "Genghis Khan",
            "Genghis",
            "Chinggis Khan",
            "Chinggis"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Were ruled by what man, who met with Marco Polo and twice failed to invade Japan?",
          "answer": [
            "Kublai Khan",
            "Kublai"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Founded which colorful state that dominated Russia until the rise of Muscovy?",
          "answer": "Golden Horde"
        },
        {
          "question": "Founded which Chinese dynasty in 1271?",
          "answer": [
            "Yuan Dynasty",
            "Yuan"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Conquered what preceding Chinese dynasty, crushing them in the Battle of Yamen?",
          "answer": [
            "Song Dynasty",
            "Song"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Built what 13th century capital city after Ogedei defeated the Jin?",
          "answer": "Karakorum"
        }
      ],
      "prompt": "The Mongols..."
    },
    {
      "category": "POLITICAL UPHEAVAL AROUND THE WORLD",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Ioannis Metaxas, who restored order to the streets of Athens in 1936?",
          "answer": "Greece"
        },
        {
          "question": "A CIA-MI5 alliance that installed a pro-western Shah in Tehran?",
          "answer": "Iran"
        },
        {
          "question": "anti-Erdogan [air-doh-wan] protesters, who were fought back by tanks in Istanbul in 2016?",
          "answer": "Turkey"
        },
        {
          "question": "1945’s Kyujo incident, in which officers wanted to stop this country from surrendering World War II?",
          "answer": "Japan"
        },
        {
          "question": "Hafez al-Assad, who established a Baathist government in 1963 that is now led by his son, Bashar?",
          "answer": "Syria"
        },
        {
          "question": "Getulio Vargas, who started the Estado Novo dictatorship?",
          "answer": "Brazil"
        },
        {
          "question": "Generals seeking to enforce lese majeste [lez mah-jest-ay] laws that protected Rama IX [ninth] in\nSoutheast Asia?",
          "answer": "Thailand"
        },
        {
          "question": "Alberto Fujimori, who defeated the communist Shining Path insurgency in South America?",
          "answer": "Peru"
        }
      ],
      "prompt": "Which country was the site of the coup d’etat of..."
    },
    {
      "category": "THE TANG DYNASTY",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Created a monopoly on what food flavoring obtained from evaporated seawater?",
          "answer": "salt"
        },
        {
          "question": "Claimed descent from the founder of which Chinese philosophy, which deals with yin and yang?",
          "answer": [
            "Taoism",
            "Tao",
            "Daoism",
            "Dao"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Ruled millions of people with this ethnicity, which shares its name with the second imperial dynasty\nof China?",
          "answer": [
            "Han",
            "Han dynasty"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Tried conducting what kind of survey to determine how many people lived in the empire?",
          "answer": "census"
        },
        {
          "question": "Brought the Mahayana sect of what religion to prominence to China?",
          "answer": [
            "Buddhism",
            "Buddhist"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Expanded what system to select candidates for the civil service in China?",
          "answer": [
            "Imperial examinations",
            "exam",
            "civil service examinations"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Was interrupted by what only female Empress of China?",
          "answer": [
            "Wu Zetian",
            "Wu"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Succeeded what short-lived dynasty that managed to reunify China and built the Grand Canal?",
          "answer": [
            "Sui Dynasty",
            "Sui"
          ]
        }
      ],
      "prompt": "The Tang Dynasty..."
    },
    {
      "category": "THE VIETNAM WAR",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Was ended under which U.S. President, who succeeded Nixon without receiving a vote for President?",
          "answer": [
            "Gerald Ford",
            "Ford"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Ended with a withdrawal from the American embassy in what capital city of South Vietnam?",
          "answer": "Saigon"
        },
        {
          "question": "Involved North Vietnamese boats firing on the USS Maddox in what Gulf?",
          "answer": [
            "Gulf of Tonkin",
            "Tonkin"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Included what 1968 offensive, conducted on a Vietnamese holiday, that helped turn U.S. public\nopinion against the war?",
          "answer": [
            "Tet Offensive",
            "Tet"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Included what March 1968 massacre of Vietnamese citizens at “Pinkville”?",
          "answer": [
            "My Lai Massacre",
            "My Lai"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Involved massive deforestation via the spraying of what toxic chemical?",
          "answer": [
            "Agent Orange",
            "Orange"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Involved bombings of what North Vietnamese supply trail that went through Laos and Cambodia?",
          "answer": [
            "Ho Chi Minh Trail",
            "Ho Chi Minh"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Included what 3.5 year long bombing operation against North Vietnam that ended just before the\n1968 U.S. election?",
          "answer": [
            "Operation Rolling Thunder",
            "Rolling Thunder"
          ]
        }
      ],
      "prompt": "The Vietnam War..."
    },
    {
      "category": "INDIAN OCEAN TRADE",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Linked the subcontinent, around 1 AD, to which European empire that spanned the Mediterranean?",
          "answer": [
            "Roman Empire",
            "Roman",
            "Rome"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Was manipulated by which European nation that was the first to sail to India?",
          "answer": [
            "Kingdom of Portugal",
            "Portugal"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Involved ports in what region west of India, home to the Safavid Empire and namesake of a gulf south\nof it?",
          "answer": "Persia"
        },
        {
          "question": "Used the winds generated by what phenomenon that brings heavy rainfall to portions of India?",
          "answer": "monsoons"
        },
        {
          "question": "Visited which country on the tip of the Arabian peninsula, the site of a trading base at Muscat?",
          "answer": "Oman"
        },
        {
          "question": "Included the use of which massive Chinese ships used by Zheng He on his voyages?",
          "answer": "junk"
        },
        {
          "question": "Visited the East African coast, populated by speakers of which language, a mix of Arabic, Bantu, and\nother native languages?",
          "answer": "Swahili"
        },
        {
          "question": "Passed through which strait at the end of the Malayan Peninsula, which was dominated by a namesake\nsultanate?",
          "answer": [
            "Straits of Malacca",
            "Malacca"
          ]
        }
      ],
      "prompt": "A system of trade in the Indian Ocean..."
    },
    {
      "category": "Portugal",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Capital city of Portugal for centuries, minus a short stint when the court moved to Brazil.",
          "answer": "Lisbon"
        },
        {
          "question": "Italian-born explorer whose proposed 1492 voyage across the Atlantic was denied funding by the Portuguese.",
          "answer": "Christopher Columbus or Cristobal Colon"
        },
        {
          "question": "Natural disaster that struck the Portuguese capital, causing fires and a tsunami in 1755.",
          "answer": "Lisbon earthquake of 1755"
        },
        {
          "question": "First European explorer to sail to India; his travels are recorded in The Lusiads.",
          "answer": "Vasco da Gama"
        },
        {
          "question": "Prince and explorer who patronized Portuguese exploration and encouraged the conquest of Ceuta [thay-oo-tah].",
          "answer": "Henry the Navigator"
        },
        {
          "question": "Small ship whose lateen sails allowed it to sail down the West African coast.",
          "answer": "caravel"
        },
        {
          "question": "1494 treaty that divided the New World between Castile and Portugal.",
          "answer": "Treaty of Tordesillas"
        },
        {
          "question": "Final Portuguese royal house which first held the throne under John IV and later ruled Brazil under two Pedros.",
          "answer": "House of Braganza"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Explorers",
      "prompt": "Name the explorer who...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "led an expedition to the new world on the Santa Maria.",
          "answer": "Christopher Columbus"
        },
        {
          "question": "Gave a detailed account of China in his Travels.",
          "answer": "Marco Polo"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was killed in Hawaii while attempting to kidnap Kalani’opu’u.",
          "answer": "James Cook"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the first European to discover Brazil.",
          "answer": "Pedro Cabral"
        },
        {
          "question": "Discovered a direct sea route to India, starting in 1497, for Portugal.",
          "answer": "Vasco da Gama"
        },
        {
          "question": "Sailed the coast of North America in 1497 for Henry VII.",
          "answer": "John Cabot or Giovanni Caboto"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the first to sail around the southernmost tip of Africa.",
          "answer": "Bartolomeu Dias"
        },
        {
          "question": "Explored New York Bay and is the namesake of a bridge that crosses the Narrows.",
          "answer": "Giovanni da Verrazzano"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "World War II in Asia",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Country that started the fighting by invading China in 1937.",
          "answer": "Japan"
        },
        {
          "question": "Peninsula that was subject to strict rule from a puppet government in Seoul.",
          "answer": "Korean Peninsula"
        },
        {
          "question": "Region of China that was turned into a puppet kingdom under Pu Yi.",
          "answer": [
            "Manchuria",
            "Manchukuo"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "City-state founded by Stamford Raffles that was besieged.",
          "answer": "Singapore"
        },
        {
          "question": "Island where American troops raised a flag on Mount Suribachi.",
          "answer": "Iwo Jima"
        },
        {
          "question": "1942 naval battle that resulted in the destruction of the USS Lexington.",
          "answer": "Battle of the Coral Sea"
        },
        {
          "question": "1944 battle off the coast of the Philippines, possibly the largest naval battle in history.",
          "answer": "Battle of Leyte Gulf"
        },
        {
          "question": "Northern Australian city that was bombed by Japanese forces in February 1942.",
          "answer": "Darwin"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Chiang Kai-Shek",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Rival political party that took power in China after he was forced out of the country.",
          "answer": "Communist Party"
        },
        {
          "question": "Island to which he fled after the Chinese Civil War.",
          "answer": [
            "Taiwan",
            "Formosa"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "River, the second-longest in China, he had flooded to slow down invading Japanese forces.",
          "answer": "Yellow River"
        },
        {
          "question": "Political party he led, often called the Nationalists.",
          "answer": [
            "Kuomintang",
            "KMT"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Man who mentored him and put him in charge of the Whampoa Military Academy.",
          "answer": "Sun Yat-Sen"
        },
        {
          "question": "1937 incident at a bridge near Beijing that forced Chiang into the second Sino-Japanese War.",
          "answer": "Marco Polo Bridge Incident"
        },
        {
          "question": "1936 incident in which he was kidnapped and forced to create a United Front.",
          "answer": "Xi’an Incident"
        },
        {
          "question": "Wife of Chiang Kai-shek and youngest of the influential Soong sisters.",
          "answer": "Soong Mei-ling"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Martin Luther King Jr.",
      "prompt": "In what city did...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "he give his “I Have a Dream” speech at the Lincoln Memorial?",
          "answer": "Washington D.C."
        },
        {
          "question": "he write “Injustice anywhere is a threat to justice everywhere” while in jail in Alabama?",
          "answer": "Birmingham"
        },
        {
          "question": "he support an Alabama bus boycott sparked by Rosa Parks?",
          "answer": "Montgomery"
        },
        {
          "question": "he lead a march across the Edmund Pettus Bridge?",
          "answer": "Selma"
        },
        {
          "question": "he support striking sanitation workers in Tennessee before being assassinated?",
          "answer": "Memphis"
        },
        {
          "question": "crowds, upset at his death, not riot after being calmed by an impromptu Robert Kennedy speech?",
          "answer": "Indianapolis"
        },
        {
          "question": "he move to North Lawndale in 1966 to support open housing?",
          "answer": "Chicago"
        },
        {
          "question": "King support Robert Hayling’s movement, which included a “dive-in” at the Monson Motor Lodge swimming pool?",
          "answer": "St. Augustine"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Southeast Asian Countries",
      "prompt": "Name the modern Southeast Asian country...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "That declared independence from Spain in 1898 and gained it from the US in 1946 F",
          "answer": "Republic of the Philippines"
        },
        {
          "question": "Where the Battle of Dien Bien Phu was fought, once divided into North and South",
          "answer": "Socialist Republic of Vietnam"
        },
        {
          "question": "Where the Khmer Rouge led by Pol Pot carried out genocide resulting in the infamous “killing fields”",
          "answer": [
            "Kingdom of Cambodia",
            "Kampuchea A"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Once led by Lee Kuan Yew and founded as a colony by Stamford Raffles",
          "answer": "Republic of Singapore"
        },
        {
          "question": "Whose president Suharto led from its capital Jakarta",
          "answer": "Republic of Indonesia"
        },
        {
          "question": "Home to 1990 Nobel Peach Prize winner Aung San Suu Kyi [CHEE], its first State Counsellor",
          "answer": [
            "Republic of the Union of Myanmar",
            "Burma R"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "The site of military coups against Thaksin Shinawatra and his sister Yingluck",
          "answer": "Kingdom of Thailand"
        },
        {
          "question": "Once led by Mahathir Mohamad and embroiled in the 1MDB political scandal.",
          "answer": "Malaysia D T"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Vietnam War",
      "prompt": "Concerning the Vietnam War, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Democratic president whose policies led to the highest number of U.S. ground troops.",
          "answer": "Lyndon Baines Johnson or LBJ"
        },
        {
          "question": "Republican president who gradually pulled out of the war through his policy of Vietnamization.",
          "answer": "Richard Milhous Nixon"
        },
        {
          "question": "Neighboring Southeast Asian nation which, along with Laos, was secretly bombed.",
          "answer": "Kingdom of Cambodia or Preahreacheanachakr Kampuchea"
        },
        {
          "question": "South Vietnamese capital whose 1975 fall signaled the end of the war.",
          "answer": "Saigon or Ho Chi Minh City"
        },
        {
          "question": "1968 \"Offensive\" named for a holiday, which included the Hue [[WAY]] Massacre and the Battle of Khe Sanh [[KAY SAHN]].",
          "answer": "Tet Offensive or Sự kiện Tết Mậu Thân"
        },
        {
          "question": "North Vietnamese-supported guerillas who fought against U.S. forces.",
          "answer": "Viet Cong or National Liberation Front of South Vietnam"
        },
        {
          "question": "Carcinogenic defoliant used by the U.S. army to destroy Vietnamese agriculture and lessen jungle thickness.",
          "answer": "Agent Orange"
        },
        {
          "question": "1964 \"Incident\" named for a body of water which was cited as an impetus for increasing the U.S. presence.",
          "answer": "Gulf of Tonkin Incident"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Mexico in the 20th century",
      "prompt": "Concerning Mexico, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Revolutionary during the Mexican Civil War whose raid on Columbus, New Mexico triggered a failed U.S. manhunt.",
          "answer": "Francisco \"Pancho\"Villaor José DoroteoArangoArámbula"
        },
        {
          "question": "Popular moderate president who was assassinated during the Ten Tragic Days of the Mexican Revolution.",
          "answer": "FranciscoMaderoor Francisco IgnacioMaderoGonzález 2021-22 C Set History"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "French Colonialism in Africa",
      "prompt": "Concerning French imperialism, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Kingdom which became a French protectorate following the Treaty of Fes.",
          "answer": "Kingdom ofMorocco"
        },
        {
          "question": "North African nation whose FLN fought a civil war with the French in the 1950s and 1960s.",
          "answer": "People's Democratic Republic ofAlgeria"
        },
        {
          "question": "Horn of Africa nation and neighbor to Ethiopia once known as French Somaliland.",
          "answer": [
            "Republic ofDjibouti",
            "République deDjibouti",
            "or JumhūrīyahJībūtī"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Former West African colony whose first president, Leopold Senghor, founded the literary movement Negritude.",
          "answer": "Republic ofSenegalor République duSénégal"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Malaysia",
      "prompt": "Concerning the nation of Malaysia, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Wealthy city-state which was expelled in 1965.",
          "answer": "Republic ofSingapore"
        },
        {
          "question": "Powerful medieval state which shares its name with a \"Strait\" separating the Malay peninsula from Sumatra.",
          "answer": "Sultanate ofMalacca"
        },
        {
          "question": "Neighbor who annexed its northern reaches during World War Two as a member of the Japanese Co-Prosperity Sphere.",
          "answer": "Kingdom ofThailandorSiam"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) (TIEBREAKER EXAMPLE QUESTION) At the end of this war, the Penghu (pr. PEN-goo) Islands changed hands, as did the\nLiaodong (luh-OW-dong) Peninsula. (20 pts) ",
        "The Port Arthur Massacre occurred during this\nwar, which ended with the transfer of the Pescadores (PESS-cuh-doorz) and Taiwan. (10 pts) ",
        "For 10 points, name this war ended by the Treaty of Shimonoseki (shim-OH-noh-SEK-ee)\nbetween two Asian powers in 1895."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Sino-Japanese War",
        "Sino-Japanese",
        "First Sino-Japanese War",
        "Jiawu War",
        "Jiawu",
        "Japan–Qing War",
        "Japan–Qing"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) These people were the target of 1913's Alien Land Law. These people were guaranteed\nequal access to public schools as part of the (20 pts) ",
        "\"Gentlemen's Agreement\" which restricted\ntheir further immigration. They were later relocated to facilities such as Manzanar as part\nof a practice upheld by the (10 pts) ",
        "Supreme Court in the Korematsu case. For 10 points, name this\ngroup which was subject to World War II \"internment\" on the West Coast."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Japanese-Americans",
        "Japanese"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The Central Asian conquerors known as the Hepthalites are also called the \"white\"\nversion of these people, who may also be identical to the Chinese (20 pts) ",
        "Xiongnu (pr. shongNOO). These people advanced into Western Europe shortly after the death of Bleda, and in\n452, Pope Leo I negotiated a retreat of their forces from Rome. (10 pts) ",
        "For 10 points, name these\nconquerors who briefly dominated Eastern Europe under the leadership of Attila."
      ],
      "answer": "Huns"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Kicking Bear adapted a Mormon belief into an auxiliary practice of this movement, in\nwhich bullet-repelling shirts were worn. This movement's main ritual was adapted from\nearlier \"circle\" performances by (20 pts) ",
        "Wodziwob, and it spread across the Plains under the\nleadership of (10 pts) ",
        "Wovoka, who preached that it would end white encroachment on Indian lands.\nFor 10 points, name this Indian religious movement whose practitioners were massacred in 1890\nat Wounded Knee."
      ],
      "answer": "Ghost Dance"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This language was used to write a play in which a woman loses a ring in a river that\nwould prove her identity to her husband. In addition to that play by (20 pts) ",
        "Kalidasa, this\nlanguage was used to write four religious texts called the Vedas. In one epic written in this\nlanguage, a prince saves his wife (10 pts) ",
        "Sita after she is kidnapped by Ravana. For ten points, name\nthis classical language of India used to write the Ramayana, Mahabharata, and most Hindu literature."
      ],
      "answer": "Sanskrit"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) (TIEBREAKER EXAMPLE QUESTION) This event’s capture of Gwailor by forces under Tatya Tose preceded that man’s\nbetrayal at the hands of Man (20 pts) ",
        "Singh. Henry Havelock and Henry Lawrence died\nduring a siege in this event that also saw the Storming of Secundra Bagh and the\nsiege of (10 pts) ",
        "Lucknow. It began after a rumor that the new Enfield Rifles were being lubricated\nwith cow and pig fat. For ten points, name this 1857 Indian rebellion against Great Britiain."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Sepoy Mutiny",
        "Sepoy Rebellion",
        "Sepoy"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The Onna-bugeisha were female members of this class, and dissatisfied members of\nthis class rebelled in the Satsuma (20 pts) ",
        "Rebellion. Members of this class were trained in\nKyujutsu, the ability to use the Yumi. Lordless members of this class were labeled (10 pts) ",
        "Ronin,\nand the values of this class are often presented as Bushido. For ten points, name this Japanese warrior\nclass that is often depicted using katanas."
      ],
      "answer": "Samurai"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Project Seal attempted to use bombs to generate these events. They have low amplitude\nbut long (20 pts) ",
        "wavelength, which make them difficult to detect until they undergo shoaling\nin shallow areas. (10 pts) ",
        "Warnings about the oncoming of these events are issued from a center in Hawai’i.\nFor ten points, floods in Japanese coastal cities are often due to what kind of very large wave that is\ntypically caused by an earthquake?"
      ],
      "answer": "tsunami"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One of these conflicts was triggered by the seizure of a ship believed to be held by\npirates, the Arrow. Lin Zexu served as a naval commander during the first of these wars\nthat was ended with the Treaty of the (20 pts) ",
        "Bogue. Another of these wars was started by\nthe Kowloon Incident. Their aftermath ended the (10 pts) ",
        "Canton System with the “unequal treaty”\nof Nanking. For ten points, name these 19th century wars fought in China over a drug processed from\npoppies."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Opium Wars",
        "Opium"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A road named for this man was the target of Operation Barrel Roll. This man, who\ntried to oppose French colonialism in his home country at the Treaty of (20 pts) ",
        "Versailles, used\nSoviet and Chinese support to build an army capable of defeating the French at Dien (10 pts) ",
        "Bien Phu. He authorized the Tet Offensive, the turning point of a war that ended after this man’s death\nwith the fall of Saigon. For ten points, name this victorious North Vietnamese leader, now the namesake\nof Vietnam’s largest city."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Ho Chi Minh",
        "Ho"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) (TIEBREAKER EXAMPLE QUESTION) Holders of this position possessed the Heirloom Seal of the Realm and ranked\ntheir consorts and concubines. The first holder of this position, a (20 pts) ",
        "Legalist, ended\nthe Warring States period, burned books, and was buried with an army of terracotta\nwarriors. The (10 pts) ",
        "Mandate of Heaven empowered, for ten points, what position held by Qin Shi\nHuangdi and hundreds of other Middle Kingdom leaders?"
      ],
      "answer": "Emperor of China"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A use of this technology by the Kingdom of Mysore was refined by William Congreve.\nThe introduction of another form of this technology allowed Hongi Hika to win inter-tribal\nwars among the (20 pts) ",
        "Maori on New Zealand. Ottoman Janissaries were trained in using this\ntechnology under Mehmed the Conqueror. (10 pts) ",
        "Guy Fawkes’s failed plot to destroy Parliament\ninvolved barrels of, for ten points, what volatile material, a mixture of saltpeter, sulfur, and charcoal\nwhose invention in 9th century China led to the development of hand cannons and modern projectile\nweapons?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "gunpowder",
        "black powder",
        "Congreve rockets",
        "rocket",
        "Musket War",
        "Musket"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This diplomat re-assigned Archer Blood within his department, rather than respond to\nthe Blood Telegram warning of genocide during the Bangladesh War. This Cabinet member\nbegan the policy of d´etente with the (20 pts) ",
        "USSR and worked to normalize relations with\nChina. This man was co-recognized with Le Duc Tho for their work on the Paris Peace\nAccords; Le Duc Tho refused that Nobel Peace Prize, as the (10 pts) ",
        "Vietnam War had not actually\nended. For ten points, name this Secretary of State under Presidents Nixon and Ford."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Henry Kissinger",
        "Kissinger"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man lived in exile for several years in a Novotel Hotel, where he was interviewed\nby Brian Barron. This ruler allowed Air France Flight 139 to land in his nation, leading (20 pts) ",
        "Israel to retaliate with Operation Entebbe. This ally of Muammar Gaddafi and former\nofficer of the King’s African Rifles declared himself King of (10 pts) ",
        "Scotland and forced all Asians\nin his country to leave, but was overthrown after a failed attempt to annex Kagara from Tanzania. For\nten points, name this eccentric Ugandan dictator during the 1970s."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Idi Amin Dada",
        "Idi Amin"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A kingdom in this region launched the Gihae Eastern Expedition to eradicate piracy on\na nearby island. The Silla kingdom ruled this location until its 935 annexation by the (20 pts) ",
        "Goryeo dynasty, which helped provide this location’s name. A phonetic alphabet native to\nthis region, hangul, was introduced by (10 pts) ",
        "Sejong the Great of the Joseon Dynasty, who sought an\nalliance with Ming China. For ten points, name this East Asian peninsula that has been divided between\ntwo countries since a 1950s war."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Korean Peninsula",
        "Korea"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A prominent port on this body of water was once ruled by a zamorin and was the most\ndominant city on the Malabar Coast. During the Ming Dynasty, Zheng He asserted Chinese\ndominance over (20 pts) ",
        "trade routes in and around this ocean. To reach Calicut, Vasco da\nGama rounded the Cape of (10 pts) ",
        "Good Hope and sailed along and across this body of water. The\nendpoint of the Brahmaputra and Ganges rivers is, for ten points, what South Asian ocean between Africa\nand Australia?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Indian Ocean",
        "Indian",
        "Arabian Sea",
        "Arabian"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) During his time as governor of Africa, this man was pelted by turnips and found himself in financial difficulty, causing him to turn to the mule trade. This man fell out of imperial favor after falling asleep during one of (20 pts)",
        "Nero’s lyre recitals. During the Great Jewish Revolt, this man threw captured prisoners into the Dead Sea to test its legendary buoyancy; that revolt was later crushed by his son (10 pts)",
        "Titus. For ten points, name this founder of the Flavian dynasty, the last Emperor during the Year of the Four Emperors."
      ],
      "answer": "Vespasian or Titus Flavius Caesar Vespasianus Augustus, but"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) During this event, a fact-finding mission was dispatched on a world tour that recommended basing its country’s army and parliament on Prussia’s. This event was preceded by a war during which the Republic of Ezo was declared, the (20 pts)",
        "Boshin War. This event provoked a rebellion among disenfranchised warriors in Satsuma province, and the Charter Oath was issued during this event. This event marked the (10 pts)",
        "end of a period that had begun with Tokugawa Ieyasu’s conquest of Japan 250 years earlier. For ten points, name this late 1860s event during which power was given back to Japan’s imperial house."
      ],
      "answer": "Meiji Restoration"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) UN Resolution 498 condemned a nation for intervening in this war. A key strategic region for one side in this war was the Iron Triangle, which was successfully defended at the Battle of Triangle Hill. One side in this war was accused of using human-wave attacks to overwhelm enemy defenses and was led by (20 pts)",
        "Peng Dehuai. Omar Bradley said that one general’s plan to extend the theater of this war was “the wrong war, at the wrong place, at the wrong time, and with the wrong enemy.” (10 pts)",
        "Douglas MacArthur’s advance towards the Yalu River in this war led to a counterattack of millions of Chinese soldiers. For ten points, name this war fought on a now-divided East Asian peninsula."
      ],
      "answer": "Korean War or Han zhan"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Note: two answers required. Disputes over a glacier between these two countries inspired the term oropolitics. A 1965 war between these two countries occurred after one of them launched the failed Operation Gibraltar and was ended by the Tashkent Declaration. These two countries were separated by the (20 pts)",
        "Radcliffe Line, which has been superseded by the Line of Control and Zero Point. The Siachen Glacier has been contested between these two countries, which have engaged in (10 pts)",
        "Cricket Diplomacy in order to reduce tensions. For ten points, name these two South Asian countries that have fought four wars since 1947, when they were partitioned from each other in their independence from Britain."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "India and Pakistan",
        "in either order"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One aerial assault during this battle left every attacker but George Gay dead. This battle, which was preceded by “Operation AL,” an attack on the Aleutians, was itself codenamed (20 pts)",
        "“AF” according to a code that was broken by the winning side. Indecision over arming aircraft with torpedoes or bombs cost (10 pts)",
        "Chuichi Nagumo victory in this battle, as that error led to the loss of four Japanese aircraft carriers. For ten points, name this turning point of the Pacific theater, a June 1942 naval battle fought over a namesake atoll."
      ],
      "answer": "Battle of Midway"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man’s foreign minister was assassinated by a Buddhist preacher in the League of Blood Incident. In the Kyujo Incident, a group of generals attempted to force this man into house arrest before he could (20 pts)",
        "address the nation. This man announced his acceptance of the Joint Declaration of Powers in the Jewel Voice Broadcast. After his nation (10 pts)",
        "surrendered aboard the USS Missouri, this man was forced to renounce his divinity. For ten points, name this Emperor of Japan during World War II."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Hirohito",
        "Showa"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A member of this order, Alessandro Valignano, delivered Yasuke to Japan where he later became a samurai under Oda Nobunaga. This order was allowed to use the port of (20 pts)",
        "Dejima in Nagasaki to carry out trade. This order, which was created near the start of the (10 pts)",
        "Counter-Reformation, sent Matteo Ricci to Macau to start converting the Chinese. Ignatius of Loyola founded, for ten points, what Christian order also known as the Society of Jesus?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Jesuits",
        "Society of Jesus before it is read"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) According to William Julius Wilson, this concept’s importance is declining due to the complex nature of job markets. In The Bell Curve, Charles Murray linked differences in intelligence to this concept. “One (20 pts)",
        "drop” rules have been used to classify this concept, and (10 pts)",
        "poll taxes and literacy tests were used in the Jim Crow South to discriminate based on this concept. For ten points, name this sociological concept that may be divided on census forms into types like black, white, and Asian."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "race",
        "ethnicity"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) These constructs were first accurately surveyed by William Gowland, who became known as Japan’s father of archaeology. After Suanin banned human sacrifices, Haniwa (20 pts)",
        "terracotta figures were placed inside these constructs instead. A period of rule by the Yamato clan is alternatively named for these constructs, which were constructed in keyhole shaped (10 pts)",
        "mounds following the Yayoi period. For ten points, name these constructs that were exemplified by the Japanese kofun and contained the remains of emperors."
      ],
      "answer": "Japanese tombs IHO General Bowl 2017-2018 Round 9"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In this decade, the Advanced Producers’ Co-operatives were first established. In this decade, during the Lushan [loo-SHAN] Conference, General Peng Dehuai [pun duh-HWHY] was purged as part of the (20 pts)",
        "Anti-Rightist Movement. A program named after a poem about the Warring States period began in this decade. Backyard steel production was part of a campaign launched in this decade that led to a (10 pts)",
        "famine that killed millions. For ten points, name this decade that included China’s Hundred Flowers Campaign and the Great Leap Forward."
      ],
      "answer": "1950s"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man’s quest for immortality led to the search for a 1000 year old magician at DPenglai and also to this man’s death after ingesting mercury pills. This man was tricked by a neighboring state into building a canal instead of fighting a war and was the target of a conspiracy by (20 pts)",
        "Lao Ai. This man reversed his decision to expel his foreign advisors at the urging of his future prime minister, Li Si. He ended the Warring States period by defeating the Qi and burned Confucian books as part of his Legalist philosophy. The man who began the (10 pts)",
        "Great Wall and built the Terracotta Warriors was, for ten points, what first emperor of a unified China?"
      ],
      "answer": "Qin Shi Huangdi"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One policy established by this figure was influenced by the predictions of the Club of Rome. This leader opposed support for the “Fifth Modernization,” which was advocated by the Democracy Wall movement. The death of Hu (20 pts)",
        "Yaobang [‘who” yow-bahn] triggered a series of protests against this leader which ended with military intervention. That intervention included the determined stand of (10 pts)",
        "Tank Man. For ten points, name this Chinese leader who presided over the beginning of the one-child policy, the Tiananmen Square Massacre, and China’s liberalization in the 1980s."
      ],
      "answer": "Deng Xiaoping"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man and his brother served during the British invasion under Aulus Plautius where he commanded Legio II Augusta. That brother, Sabinus, was murdered in Rome while this man’s forces approached the city in the Year of the (20 pts)",
        "Four Emperors. This man was a patron of the historian Josephus, and he said right before his death in 79 AD that “an F Emperor ought to die standing upright.” The construction of the (10 pts)",
        "Colosseum began during this man’s reign and was finished during the reign of his successor, Titus. For ten points, name this founder of the Flavian dynasty."
      ],
      "answer": "Vespasian"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In this war’s first major land battle, the Eastern Detachment was defeated at the village of Wiju. Two days after this war, an exploding magazine inadvertently destroyed the Mikasa, the flagship that began this war by launching a surprise attack on (20 pts)",
        "Port Arthur. Theodore Roosevelt won a Nobel Peace Prize for his help ending this war through the Treaty of (10 pts)",
        "Portsmouth after one side’s Baltic Fleet was defeated at Tsushima Straits. For ten points, name this war in which Meiji Japan humiliated a Western empire led by Nicholas II."
      ],
      "answer": "Russo-Japanese War"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One name for this battle was attributed to the farmer who formerly owned the plot of land upon which it was fought. The winning side in this battle launched an attack on the L’anse-au-Foulon after scaling 174-foot tall cliffs. A Native American (20 pts)",
        "crouches in despair in a Benjamin West depiction of the death of one general in this battle. This battle took place on a plateau known as the Plains of Abraham and led to the deaths of both commanders, Louis-Joseph de (10 pts)",
        "Montcalm and James Wolfe. For ten points, name this 1759 battle in which a namesake Canadian city was captured by the British in the French and Indian War."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Battle of Quebec",
        "Battle of the Plains of Abraham before it is mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A mining rights concession that this man negotiated with the Matabele king Lobengula paved the way for the creation of a namesake southern African colony. This man supported the Jameson Raid and founded the (20 pts)",
        "De Beers diamond company in Kimberley. A cartoon in Punch depicted this man as a colossus astride Africa as a result of his advocacy for a (10 pts)",
        "railroad spanning the continent from “Cape to Cairo.” For ten points, name this Victorian imperialist for whom a prestigious scholarship at Oxford university is named."
      ],
      "answer": "Cecil John Rhodes T"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "In an effort to suppress this faith, President Élie Lescot [[leh-SKOH]] launched Operation Cleanup in the 1940s. This faith overtook traditional Catholicism in the early 19th century after Jean-Jacques Dessalines [[deh-sah-LEEN]] declared (*) himself head of the state church. Many of this faith's priest caste, known as houngans [[HOONG-gahns]], gained power during the reign of Papa Doc Duvalier [[doo-vahl- YEH]]. (*) For ten points name this African diaspora religion originating in Haiti."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Haitian Vodouism",
        "Voodoo"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man, who advocated for the \"Five Races under One Union\" policy, incorporated his own Methodist beliefs into his \"New Life Movement.\" This man perpetrated the April 12th Purge of Communists (20 pts)",
        "and other workers led by Zhou Enlai [[ZHOH EN-\"LIE\"]]. This man's National Revolutionary Party formed the United Front with Mao's Red Army to (10 pts)",
        "defend against the Japanese. For ten points, name this \"Generalissimo\" of Nationalist China who fled to Taiwan in the 1940s."
      ],
      "answer": "Chiang Kai-shek"
    }
  ]
}